We're looking at these really amazing and powerful things called functions.
These are these sort of black boxes in a sense, that have all sorts of code inside of them.
We can call them and they can return values for us.
Now we know that there are lots and lots of built in functions, and there's all sorts of modules.
So you can have functions from everything from drawing type function to math functions, etc. and we
can use those functions to do lots of amazing things.
But the real power comes in when you start to create your own functions.
Why would you want to do this?
Well, it allows you to have this reusable code.
And as we'll show you now in this lesson, when you start to create functions, it makes it so much
easier to actually code because once the function is done once, it's like an amazing little magic box
that you can just use over and over and over again.
So let's have a look.
We're going to start off with a relatively simple example, just so I can show you the layout and the
syntax and basically what a function looks like.
So this is what you do to create your own function.
You start off by typing tapping this keyword def, which basically stands for define.
Because every time you type in a new function, you're basically defining a new function.
The next thing you want is to give your function a name.
So in this example I'm just going to show you how to create a function that cubes a number.
So obviously just like variables you're going to want to give your function a name that makes sense.
So let me just call my function cube.
And then functions also have the same thing with variables where you shouldn't start with a capital
letter and you shouldn't start with a number.
Okay.
So there's define cube.
The next thing we need to make this cube function work we need a parameter in here which is going to
hold the number that the user wants to cube.
So in other words it's basically a variable called num.
So this is the value that's going to be passed to the function so that it can cube that number.
So this parameter will hold that value.
Just like when you chose to call print.
Well when we did examples with print you put in a value in those brackets.
And that's how the function knew what sentence or what you wanted it to print.
Okay.
And then so how would we cube a number.
Basically what we want to do is we want to take that number times it by itself again and times it again.
And that will give us the cube of the number.
But now with functions, you want this answer to be given back to the user or returned to the user,
as we would say.
So what you actually want to do is you want to type in this word here called return.
Now I'm going to show you what happens in this one that works.
And then I'm going to show you what happens if we take it away.
So what this should do is the user is going to call the function by just typing the function's name.
And then because we have this parameter Here we have one parameter called number.
That means in order to call this function, the user has to put in a parameter.
Let's just say seven.
If the user didn't put in a parameter yet, that means that this.
That means that Python will not see this cube function as being the same as this one.
Let's just, for example, say that I'm put it in another variable here.
Let's just call it Num2.
This now no longer calls this function over here.
So you've got to check that your function has the same amount of parameters as the function you are
wanting to call.
Okay.
And then obviously we want to print this value.
If I didn't put the print statement well I'll show you what will happen.
Okay.
So all this is doing is it's taking this number seven.
And this number seven is becoming this variable num.
Just like we assign variables NUM becomes seven and then it's just going seven times seven times seven,
and it is returning that value to us.
Interestingly what's actually happening here.
We're running a function within a function.
So the print function is obviously Python's own function.
And we are passing that the result of our own function which was cube.
So cube does something returns the result, hands it to the print function which does something which
prints it on the screen.
So you can see how powerful these little things are.
Because one statement could do all of that.
Yeah.
So I also wanted to show you that this return value doesn't actually print anything.
All it does is it returns this value to this function call.
So if you never printed it you would actually it's almost a pointless function.
But if I change this to print.
Then it's going to print the value because it's going num becomes seven.
And we're just doing like a normal print statement.
Print seven times seven times seven.
Now, the reason we wouldn't really want to do that is we want it to be a cube function, because you
might now want to do a calculation with it.
And so rather than necessarily printing it the moment that Sarah's got cube seven so she could go cube
seven plus three and we could print that result or store that result in a variable, do whatever we
wanted.
So now you can see how powerful it is, because we now have this function that can actually be used
as part of a formula.
Okay.
So there you can see what I did is I now could add three to the cube of seven because it's returned
an integer.
So because it's returned integer or returned a number I can add I can subtract and do all those other
fun operations.
So that's the basic layout of a function.
Just remember you have this diff, you have your name and then you have these brackets with option with
optional parameters.
Some functions don't actually need this.
One does.
We'll get to examples where you may not need any parameters at all.
But for now know that is the layout of a function.